Guide to the Gitel P. Steed Papers 1907-1980
University of Chicago Library
Steed, Gitel P. Papers
1907-1980
46.5 linear feet (96 boxes, 2 drawers)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Gitel P. Steed (1914-1977), anthropologist. Consists primarily of research data from the Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Field Project, directed by Steed from 1949 to 1951. Data were collected from three villages in western and northern India and include life histories of informants, psychological tests, typed notes, field notebooks, photographs, genealogies, transcripts of interviews, and art work by researchers and villagers. Contains research notes collected by project participants James Silverberg, G. Morris Castairs, and Grace Langley. Also includes data from fieldwork projects on the Inuit of Greenland and Chinese immigrants in New York City, lectures, and publications about the India Project by Steed and other scholars. Also contains some of Steed's India photographs that were included in Edward Steichen's 1955 exhibit, The Family of Man.
Information on Use
Access
Series VII, Audio-Visual Materials, does not include access copies for all or part of the materials. Researchers will need to consult staff before requesting materials from this series. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Gitel P. Steed was born Gertrude Poznanski in 1914, in Columbus, Ohio, to Sara Auerbach and Jakob Poznanski. Her mother was a native of Columbus and her father, a businessman, immigrated from Poland. Shortly after her birth, Steed family moved to the Bronx, New York. She eventually attended Waleigh High School, and as a teenager adopted the Yiddish name Gitel.
In 1932 Gitel entered New York University (NYU), majoring in banking and finance, but dropped out after her first year. She later returned to NYU and in 1938 received her B.A. degree with honors in sociology and anthropology. While attending NYU Gitel lived in Greenwich Village where she developed friendships with many including the painter Rafael Soyer. She is the subject of at least two paintings by Soyer, "Girl in a White Blouse," 1932, which now hangs in the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, and "Two Girls," 1933, which is in the collections of the Smart Museum of Art, on the campus of the University of Chicago. It was at this same time that Gitel met her future husband, the artist Robert Steed.
In 1938, with financial support arranged by Ruth Benedict, she entered graduate school in anthropology at Columbia University, where she studied under Benedict for three years. During this time Gitel undertook the first two of four ethnological projects that marked her career in anthropology. The first of these projects, under the direction of Ruth Benedict, she conducted among the Blackfoot Indians in Montana. Then, from 1939 to 1941 she worked with Vilhjalmur Stefannsson on Inuit in Greenland, studying hunter-gatherer diet and subsistence patterns. This was to be the basis of her dissertation, but she never completed the Greenland project and only much later (1969) completed her dissertation, basing it on her India research. In 1941 she left Columbia and worked until 1943 as the senior editor of information at Yale University's Institute of Human Relations.
In 1944 she was invited to join the Jewish Black Book Committee. A group of writers and researchers supported by the World Jewish Congress and other anti-fascist Jewish organizations, this committee documented in detail the Nazi death campaign against Jews in Europe during World War II. The committee compiled papers subsequently published as The Black Book: The Nazi Crime Against the Jewish People (1946). Gitel contributed a 130-page section called "Strategies of Decimation" in which she documented Nazi Germany's policies and techniques of extermination.
In 1945 and again in 1947 she taught at Hunter College in New York. In 1946 she taught at Fisk University and there edited the journal Race Relations. In 1947 she married Robert Steed, and in 1953 gave birth to their only child, Andrew Hart Steed.
She began her third ethnological project in 1947 when she was invited to join the Columbia University Research in Contemporary Cultures Project. In this project, co-directed by Ruth Benedict and Margaret Mead, Steed's assignment was to work among Chinese immigrants in New York City. Some of the results of Steed's work were published in Mead and Metraux, The Study of Culture at a Distance (1953).
After a similar China project had to be canceled, Steed formulated her fourth ethnographic project, a field study in India. Funding was received through a grant from the Department of the Navy and Steed was appointed Director of the Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Project. Upon her return to the U.S. from India in 1951, Steed presented her findings in several seminars. The most in-depth of these seminars was a lecture series, run by Abram Kardiner, that she gave at Columbia University in 1953-1954. Due to a disagreement between Steed and Kardiner, the funding for the India project was discontinued.
Steed joined the faculty of Hofstra College in New York in 1962. While teaching at Hofstra, she completed her dissertation at Columbia University, "Caste and Kinship in Gujarat: The Social Use of Space" (1969). In 1970 she returned to Kasandra for four months, with her husband, at which time she interviewed many of her old informants about social change in the village. Steed remained on the faculty of Hofstra University until she died in 1977, at the age of 63.
INDIA FIELD PROJECT
The India field project was a team effort carried out between 1949 and 1951 in three different villages in northwestern and north central India. The primary research team included Steed, as Project Director; an anthropology graduate student, James Silverberg; a British psychiatrist, G. Morris Carstairs; and Steed's husband, Robert Steed. Silverberg's wife Donna also joined the team for some time, as did an assistant researcher, Cecil B. Massey. They were joined in India by a team of Indian interpreters and researchers. These included Bhagvati Masher and Kantilal Mehta, who worked as interpreters; Nandlal Dosajh, a psychologist; N. Prabhudas, an economist who conducted the land utilization survey; and Jerome D'Souza as cook. In the second year of research, the team also included an Indian assistant, Tahera, as well as Americans Grace Langley and John Koos. The three villages were "Kasandra" in Gujarat state, "Nawabpur" in Uttar Pradesh, and "Deoli" in Rajasthan. The villages were referred to by these pseudonyms throughout the project. Steed worked primarily in Kasandra for one year (1950). She started work in Nawabpur as well but had to cut her stay there short because of illness. James Silverberg worked in both Kasandra (1950) and in Nawabpur (1951), staying in each place for one year. Carstairs worked in Sujarupa village for Steed, 1949-1950. (Carstairs did separate research in Deoli in 1951-1952 and wrote "The Twice-Born" (1957) about it.)
Steed and her team of researchers made use of a variety of fieldwork methods, gathering data both on individual psychology and on social institutions. Most of their data on individual psychology they derived from detailed life histories collected from a sample of informants. These life histories comprised long sets of free-ranging interviews that were designated "personal narration," a battery
of psychodiagnostic tests (whose validity they subsequently questioned and dismissed), as well as watercolors and drawings by both adults and children. Data on social institutions were collected through survey methods as well as participant observation. They completed thorough surveys on land tenure and economic relations, and collected data on economic, political, religious, kinship, and caste organization.
Steed formulated the project within the broader agenda of culture and personality studies in anthropology. The theoretical and methodological agenda of culture and personality studies was to study the relation between individual personality and the socio-cultural context of their enculturation. Steed was interested in studying the extent to which Indian social institutions determined individual behavior and personality. Conversely, she also asked if innate psychological or personal aspects influenced institutions. She analyzed both the cultural and the psychological aspects of character formation and was interested in where these two aspects met.
In order to judge the relation of social institutions to personality formation, the researchers required a basis for comparison, and thus they chose three villages with different institutional frameworks. Kasandra and Deoli were predominantly Hindu villages, while Nawabpur was predominantly Muslim. Each of the three villages had a different land tenure system and political history as well as being linguistically distinct.
Scope Note
The Gitel P. Steed papers, dating from 1907 to 1980, have been arranged in eight series. The basic organization of materials in these series conforms closely to the organization of the papers upon their arrival. The main feature of the collection is the material on three Indian villages in Series III to V, where the bulk of the collection is found.
Research notes from the project are found in four basic forms: life histories, general notes, field notebooks, and note extracts. Life histories comprise typed transcriptions of sets of interviews with a select number of informants as well as results and notes taken on psychodiagnostic tests administered by the researchers. General notes are typed notes that the researchers maintained on a daily basis, in which they included the results of participant-observation in the village. Field notebooks are the rough, handwritten primary sources from which both of the former sets of notes were transcribed. Finally, note extracts refer to excerpts cut, sometimes in thin strips of as little as one line of type, from both the general notes and the life history material and then refiled under topical categories such as religion, economics, and caste and kinship. Steed and her team also compiled detailed topical indices to both the general notes and the life histories. The most elaborate indices appear in a subseries of Series III.
Certain conventions adopted by Steed and her research team have been maintained in the collection. These conventions include (1) the use of pseudonyms and informant numbers to protect the anonymity of informants, and (2) the analysis of life history data, psychodiagnostic tests, and general notes, which has led to duplicated material in different parts of the collection. Pseudonyms apply to both villages and individual informants within each village. The village pseudonyms and informant numbers used in this inventory are the same as those used by the research team. Informant lists found at the beginning of Series III, IV and V list basic information (name, age, gender, and caste) on each informant by number. In cases where there was no informant number provided for a particular individual, the procedure was to label these cases "unnumbered informant."
Duplication of materials in the collection occurs primarily in Series III through Series V. Excerpts of life histories are found in the subsequent topical subseries, which include government, politics and Rajputs, caste and kinship, economics, and religion. The psychodiagnostic tests are cross-filed under the life history of a particular informant and under their own subseries. The general notes are excerpted in the topical files. Furthermore, all three types of data--life histories, psychodiagnostic tests, and general notes--are in part transcripts from the field notebooks.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
The Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Field Project generated a great deal of data but publications stemming from it were relatively few. These publications included Steed's dissertation, "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat" (1969), and her 1955 paper in McKim Marriott's Village India; Silverberg's dissertation, "Peasant Behavior and Its Caste-Relevancy," University of Wisconsin, 1962; and Carstairs' "The Death of a Witch" (1983), in which he incorporated materials from a later project as well as the original project.
Subject Headings
Carstairs, G. M. (G. Morris); Bunzel, Ruth Leah, 1898-1990-; Silverberg, James; Steed, Gitel Poznanski; Steichen, Edward, 1879-1973; Columbia University. Research in Contemporary India Field Project; Anthropology; Chinese -- United States.; Ethnology -- Biographical methods.; Hindus -- India; Inuit -- Greenland; Muslims -- India; Gujarat (India) -- Social life and customs; Rajasthan (India) -- Social life and customs; Uttar Pradesh (India) -- Social life and customs; India -- Economic conditions -- 1947-; India -- Religion; India -- Social life and customs; United States -- Emigration and immigration; Photographs
INVENTORY
- Series I: Columbia University Research Contemporary Cultures Project
  This series comprises materials from Steed's research from 1947 to 1949 among Chinese immigrants in New York City. It includes transcripts of several informant life histories collected by Steed as well as a manuscript by Ruth Bunzel.
  The project, under the direction of Ruth Bunzel, was funded initially by a grant from the Human Resources Division of the Office of Naval Research, and coincided with the trend in anthropology during and just after WWII to study "culture and personality."
  Steed worked with individuals and families who had migrated to New York fromChina's Kwantung Province, and used primarily life histories, community "self-analysis," and projective, psychodiagnostic tests. She collected data on friendship and childhood, among other topics.
  - China fieldwork project statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chinese immigrant study, life histories, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chinese immigrant study, life histories, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chinese immigrant study, life histories, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chinese immigrant study, index outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bunzel, Ruth, "Explorations in Chinese Culture," manuscript, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bunzel, Ruth, "Explorations in Chinese Culture," manuscript, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: The Columbia University Research in Contemporary India Field Project
  This series contains general and preliminary material related to Steed's research work in India. The series is divided into five subseries: General Files, Seminar on Rural India, Urban Life Histories and Tests, Note Cards, and Maps And Charts. (A description of the Field Project follows the subseries description).
  Subseries 1: General Files, contains Steed's writings on the India research, including her dissertation as well as a screenplay she wrote based on characters in Kasandra; basic research materials used in the psychodiagnostic tests administered as part of the gathering of life histories; a preliminary research report; newspaper clippings, correspondence, and bibliographies; and a set of detailed inventories of the papers compiled in 1980 by James Silverberg, one of the original project team members. These inventories may be of value to the researcher who wishes to know more about the kind of material located in the files.
  Subseries 2: Seminar On Rural India, comprises the set of lectures that Steed presented at Columbia University in 1952-1953. These lectures represent her first and perhaps most thorough examination of her fieldwork material. In these lectures she clearly states her theoretical goals and research methods.
  Subseries 3: Urban Life Histories, contains material which was compiled in urban India prior to the village studies. These interviews and tests functioned in part as trials and in part as points for comparison to the subsequent rural studies.
  Subseries 4: Note Cards, includes two card boxes of field data analysis, consisting of cut and paste notes taken from the General Notes and grouped into a set of topical areas. A third box of note cards consists of reading research notes on books and articles about India.
  Subseries 5: Maps and Charts, contains maps that range in scale from the Indian sub-continent to state and district maps as well as maps of the villages produced by the research team. The charts consist of large kinship diagrams as well as posters of caste and marriage relations. Some maps from Steed's early fieldwork in Greenland are also to be found here. These latter are, however, the only material from her Inuit research in the collection.
  - Subseries 1: General Files
    - "Sacred Geography and Hierarchy in a Hindu Village," manuscript, research notes, map, Morton Klass correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Women of Gujarat," manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," dissertation draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," dissertation draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," dissertation draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Caste and Kinship in Rural Gujarat: The Social Use of Space," dissertation draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Devgar," screenplay, correspondence, ca. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Extension of Caste-Kindred Practices Beyond Kasandra," notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago, seminar discussions on "Village India," 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Hofstra University, Research in Contemporary Cultures India Project, project summary, proposals, "The Human Career," manuscript, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Hofstra University General Bulletin, course list, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mid-term examination for Anthropology 2, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Women, research notes, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notes, reprint, manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Rorschach test, location charts, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Rorschach test, test cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Thematic Apperception Test (TAT), small cards, negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Thematic Apperception Test (TAT), card list, comparisons from Bakrana and Adhon, notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Horn-Hellersberg (H-H) test, instructions for researcher, informant list, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Child Development Test, description, materials, notes, 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Glossaries, Hindustani, Gujerati, body language, medical terms, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Methods of Selecting Appropriate Villages," report, calendar, November 1949-January 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Preliminary report, November 15, 1949-January 31, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Caste ranking questionnaire, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - India's tribes and caste, population charts, lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sarabhai, Gautam, correspondence, project objectives, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Steward, Julian, correspondence, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - American University, Special Operations Research Office, correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - All India Sociology Conference, schedule, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Linguistic map of India, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Bibliographies, undated, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "New India in the Making," review of Development for Free Asia by Maurice Zinkin, Times Literary Supplement, January 25, 1957 - Moved to Box 89, Folder 5 (oversize) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notes, newspaper clippings, reprint, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Caste, newspaper clipping, translation from Tamil and Telugu, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Consultant forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Reading research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - James Silverberg, classified index categories, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - James Silverberg, "leftover problems," 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - James Silverberg, indexing notecards (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - James Silverberg, indexing notecards (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - James Silverberg, indexing notecards (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - James Silverberg, Kasandra, inventory of Steed papers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - James Silverberg, Kasandra, inventory of Steed papers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - James Silverberg, Kasandra, inventory of Steed papers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - James Silverberg, Kasandra, notes on economics, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - James Silverberg, Adhon, inventory of Steed papers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - James Silverberg, Deoli, inventory of Steed papers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Seminar on Rural India
    - Lecture 1, "Introduction," September 24, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Lecture 2, Project personnel and methods, October 1, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Lecture 3, Demographics, "Living Space," October 8, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Lecture 4, Dr. Abram Kardiner on sexuality and personality, October 15, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Lecture 5, "Living Space," October 22, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Lecture 6, "Reactions to Strangers in Village India," October 29, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Lecture 7, "The Structure of Village Localism," November 5, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Lecture 8, "Agrarian Class Structure under Talukdari," November 12, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Lecture 9, "Village Governing Authority," November 19, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Lecture 10, "Caste in the Village Social Matrix," December 3, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Lecture 11, "Caste, Clan, and Family," fragment, December 10, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Lecture 11, "Caste, Clan, and Family," fragment, December 10, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Lecture 12, fragment, December 17, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lectures 11 and 12, drafts, December 10-17, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Lecture 13, "Brief Introduction to Religious Experience and Thought," January 5, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Lecture 14, Religion, February 4, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Lecture 14, Religion, February 4, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Lecture 14, Religion, February 4, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Lecture 14, Religion, February 4, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Lecture 15, Religion, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Lecture 15, Religion, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Lecture 16, Religion, February 18, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Lectures 15 and 16, fragments, notes 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Lectures 15 and 16, fragments, notes 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lecture 17, Kinship, family, and child-rearing, draft, photograph, February 25, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Lecture 17, "Random Notes," February 25, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Lecture 18, Kinship and family, March 5, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Lecture 19, Rorschach interpretation, March 11, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lecture 20, Socialization, March 18, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Lecture 21, March 25, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Lecture 21, March 25, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Lecture 22, Rorschach case histories, April 1, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 10)